<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd" [
   <!ENTITY appversion "1.0"> 
   <!ENTITY manrevision "1.0"> 
   <!ENTITY date "September 2009"> 
   <!ENTITY app "<application>OpenSolaris Network Auto-Magic Online Help</application>"> 
   <!ENTITY appname "nwam-manager"> 
]>
<book id="osnetautomagoh" label="fcs" lang="en"><title>OpenSolaris Network Auto-Magic Online Help</title>
<bookinfo><authorgroup><author><firstname>Oracle Solaris</firstname>
<surname>Publications</surname>
</author>
</authorgroup>
<pubsnumber>820-7604-10</pubsnumber>
<releaseinfo></releaseinfo>
<pubdate>March 2010</pubdate>
<publisher role="maintainer"><publishername>Oracle Corporation</publishername>
</publisher>
<revhistory>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>OpenSolaris Network Auto-Magic Configuration Manual V1.0</revnumber>
      <date>September 2009</date>
	<revdescription>
          <para role="author">Sun Documentation Team </para>
          <para role="publisher">Sun Microsystems, Inc.</para>
	</revdescription>
  </revision>
</revhistory>
<abstract role="description">
       <para>
         Online help manual for OpenSolaris Network Auto-Magic Configuration.
       </para>
</abstract>
<copyright><year>2010</year>
</copyright>
<abstract><para>This online help provides detailed instructions for using the NWAM GUI to monitor network connectivity and to configure wired and wireless network connections.</para>
</abstract>
<legalnotice><para>This software and related documentation are provided under a license agreement containing restrictions on use and disclosure and are protected by intellectual property laws. Except as expressly permitted in your license agreement or allowed by law, you may not use, copy, reproduce, translate, broadcast, modify, license, transmit, distribute, exhibit, perform, publish, or display any part, in any form, or by any means. Reverse engineering, disassembly, or decompilation of this software, unless required by law for interoperability, is prohibited.</para>
<para>The information contained herein is subject to change without notice and is not warranted to be error-free. If you find any errors, please report them to us in writing.</para>
<para>If this is software or related software documentation that is delivered to the U.S. Government or anyone licensing it on behalf of the U.S. Government, the following notice is applicable:</para>
<para>U.S. GOVERNMENT RIGHTS Programs, software, databases, and related documentation and technical data delivered to U.S. Government customers are &#8220;commercial computer software&#8221; or &#8220;commercial technical data&#8221; pursuant to the applicable Federal Acquisition Regulation and agency-specific supplemental regulations. As such, the use, duplication, disclosure, modification, and adaptation shall be subject to the restrictions and license terms set forth in the applicable Government contract, and, to the extent applicable by the terms of the Government contract, the additional rights set forth in FAR 52.227-19, Commercial Computer Software License (December 2007). Oracle USA, Inc., 500 Oracle Parkway, Redwood City, CA 94065.</para>
<para>This software or hardware is developed for general use in a variety of information management applications. It is not developed or intended for use in any inherently dangerous applications, including applications which may create a risk of personal injury. If you use this software or hardware in dangerous applications, then you shall be responsible to take all appropriate fail-safe, backup, redundancy, and other measures to ensure the safe use. Oracle Corporation and its affiliates disclaim any liability for any damages caused by use of this software or hardware in dangerous applications.</para>
<para>Oracle is a registered trademark of Oracle Corporation and/or its affiliates. Oracle and Java are registered trademarks of Oracle and/or its affiliates. Other names may be trademarks of their respective owners.</para>
<para>AMD, Opteron, the AMD logo, and the AMD Opteron logo are trademarks or registered trademarks of Advanced Micro Devices. Intel and Intel Xeon are trademarks or registered trademarks of Intel Corporation. All SPARC trademarks are used under license and are trademarks or registered trademarks of SPARC International, Inc. UNIX is a registered trademark licensed through X/Open Company, Ltd.</para>
<para>This software or hardware and documentation may provide access to or information on content, products, and services from third parties. Oracle Corporation and its affiliates are not responsible for and expressly disclaim all warranties of any kind with respect to third- party content, products, and services. Oracle Corporation and its affiliates will not be responsible for any loss, costs, or damages incurred due to your access to or use of third- party content, products, or services.</para>
</legalnotice>
</bookinfo>
<chapter id="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<para>Use this online help to find out more about configuring your automatic network connection by using the Network Auto-Magic (NWAM) graphical user interface (GUI). Links within the application take you to pages that provide more detailed information. You can also navigate through this help by using links that appear within the text or by clicking the various topics in the side pane.</para>
<sect1 id="nwam-components"><title>About the Network Auto-Magic Process</title>
<para>The NWAM service simplifies basic network configuration by automatically configuring and managing your wired and wireless networks. The NWAM service addresses basic Ethernet and wireless configurations and enables you to perform various networking tasks, such as connecting to your wired or wireless network at startup and configuring new wired or wireless networks. The NWAM service also simplifies more complex network configurations, such as system-wide network configuration. In addition, this feature displays informational messages about the current status of your network connection and the overall health of your network.</para>
<para>Other feature capabilities include:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Multiple concurrent network connections</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Detection of hot-plug events</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Network modifiers support, for example, virtual private network (VPN) client applications.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Network configuration is managed by storing desired property values in the form of profiles. The service determines which profile should be active at a given time, depending on the current network conditions, then activates that profile.</para>
<para>There are two primary profile types: the <emphasis>Network Profile</emphasis>, which specifies the configuration of individual network interfaces, and <emphasis>Locations</emphasis>, which specify system-wide network configuration. The individual components that make up the network profile are referred to as <emphasis>network connections</emphasis>. You can use this application to configure and manage both types of profiles.</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Related Information</emphasis></para>
<para><xref linkend="configure-network"/>.</para>
<para><xref linkend="nwprofiles-configuring"/>.</para>
<para><xref linkend="nwlocations-overview"/>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="nwstatus-icon"><title>About the Network Status Notification Icon</title>
<para>The <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon is displayed in the desktop panel's notification area at all times. The icon is the primary method for viewing the status of your network and for interacting with automatic network configuration processes. The <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon is also where informational messages appear. The icon menu enables quick access to essential network functionality.</para>
<para>The icon's appearance indicates the overall condition of your network.</para>
<para>The following table illustrates the individual icon elements that are displayed on the desktop, along with a description.</para>
<informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="41.05*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="37.53*"/>
<colspec colwidth="62.52*"/>
<thead><row><entry><para>Icon</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Status</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody><row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/panel-wired-connect.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>All online (Wired)</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Indicates all manually enabled connections that are in the active network profile are online and that the required number of connections in the active profile group (if such a group exists) are online.</para>
<para>The &#8220;required number&#8221; is as follows:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para> One connection if the group is of the Exclusive priority type</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>One or more connections if the group is of the Shared priority type</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>All connections in the group if the group is of the All priority type</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information, see <xref linkend="prioritygrp-tasks"/></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/panel-wireless-connect.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>All online (Wireless)</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Indicates all manually enabled connections in the active network profile are online and that the required number of connections in the active profile group (if such a group exists) are online. The required number is the same as those described for the <emphasis> All online (Wired)</emphasis> status.</para>
<para>Note that at least one online connection is wireless.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/panel-some-disconnect.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>Partially online (Wired)</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Indicates one or more manually enabled or priority group connections are offline, such that the status is no longer <emphasis>All online</emphasis>. In this example, at least one wired connection is online.</para>
<para>The Network Status notification icon is also displayed as <emphasis>Partially online</emphasis> if a wireless connection is pending user input, for example choosing an available wireless network or providing a wireless network password.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/panel-all-disconnect.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>Offline (Wired)</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Indicates the NWAM service is disabled or in maintenance mode.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>If one wireless network connection is enabled, its current wireless signal strength is displayed. If multiple wireless network connections are enabled, their average signal strength is displayed.</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>To display a summary of the current network status in a tooltip, hover your mouse over the icon.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To configure network preferences, click the icon to open the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog. This function is only enabled for user accounts that have been assigned the <literal>Network Autoconf Admin</literal> rights profile by a system administrator.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To display the menu for the notification icon, right-click the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Related Information</emphasis></para>
<para><xref linkend="locationprefs-dialog"/>.</para>
<para><xref linkend="status-contxtmenu"/>.</para>
<sect1 id="connection-names"><title>How Connection Names Are Displayed</title>
<para>When viewing information about your network, note that connection names are displayed with the format, <replaceable>interface-type</replaceable> (<emphasis>link-name</emphasis>):</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para><replaceable>interface-type</replaceable> is "Wired" or "Wireless".</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>link-name</emphasis> is the link's vanity name, for example <literal>net0</literal>.</para>
<para>If the vanity name has not been defined, <emphasis>link-name</emphasis> is the default device name.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="status-contxtmenu"><title>Working With the Network Status Notification Icon Menu</title>
<para>To display the contents of this menu, right-click the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon.</para>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/nwstatus-context-menu.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
<para>The <literal>Network Status</literal> notification's icon menu is made up of the following five sections:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para><guimenuitem>Location</guimenuitem></para>
<para>This section contains a submenu that lists each available network location (shown in the following table). The current location is indicated by a radio button indicator.</para>
<informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="26.42*"/>
<colspec colwidth="28.45*"/>
<colspec colwidth="44.14*"/>
<thead><row><entry><para>Icon</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Location Type</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Location Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody><row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/system-location.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>System</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Applies only to system-provided locations (Automatic and No Network). Indicates that the system determines when to activate these locations.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/manual-location.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>Manual</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Can be manually activated or deactivated by using the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog or the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/condition-location.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>Conditional</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Location is activated or deactivated automatically according to user-defined rules.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>To activate a location other than the current location, choose the new location from the menu.</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>When the <guilabel>Switch locations automatically</guilabel> option is selected on the menu, you have no manual control over location changes. In this case, all of the locations in the submenu are unavailable (grayed-out), and the most appropriate System or Conditional location will be activated automatically in response to changes in the network environment.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>When the <guilabel>Switch locations manually</guilabel> option is selected on the menu, you have full control over location changes. In this case, any location in the submenu can be activated by choosing it, regardless of its activation type. Any location you activate in this manner remains active until you either activate a different location or choose the <guilabel>Switch locations automatically</guilabel> menu option.</para>
<para>This submenu also includes a <guimenuitem>Network Locations</guimenuitem> menu item that opens the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog. See <xref linkend="nwlocations-overview"/>. The <guimenuitem>Network Locations</guimenuitem> menu item is only enabled for user accounts that have been assigned the <literal>Network Autoconf Admin</literal> rights profile by a system administrator.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Connections</guimenuitem></para>
<para>This section contains a list of network connections in the current network profile. Enabled connections are indicated by a check mark. To manually enable or disable a connection, check or uncheck it in the menu.</para>
<note><para>Connections that belong to a priority group in the active network profile cannot be enabled or disabled manually, and are shown as unavailable (grayed-out) in the submenu. For more about priority groups, see <xref linkend="prioritygrp-tasks"/>.</para>
</note>
<para>This submenu also contains a <guimenuitem>Network Profile</guimenuitem> menu item that opens the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog, where the network profile can be switched or edited. For more information, see <xref linkend="profiles-switching"/>. The <guimenuitem>Network Profile</guimenuitem> menu item is only enabled for user accounts that have been assigned the <literal>Network Autoconf Admin</literal> rights profile by a system administrator.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Available wireless networks</guimenuitem></para>
<para>This section contains a combined list of available favorite wireless networks and all of the other currently available networks that are broadcasting their <emphasis>wireless network name</emphasis>.</para>
<para>Each available wireless network name is displayed, along with icons that represent its current signal strength and security type (open or secure). Any networks to which you are currently connected are indicated with a check mark.</para>
<para>If multiple wireless interfaces are enabled in the current network profile, each wireless network name appears on the submenu once per enabled wireless interface. A wireless link name is shown in parentheses after each network name, to enable you to view and control which wireless interface is connected to which network.</para>
<para>If a wireless network is an ad-hoc (peer-to-peer) network, "ad-hoc" is shown in parentheses next to its network name.</para>
<para>If no networks are available, a single disabled <guimenuitem>No wireless networks detected</guimenuitem> menu item is displayed.</para>
<para>If all wireless connections are disabled in the active network profile, a single disabled menu item, <guimenuitem>No wireless connections enabled</guimenuitem>, is shown. If there are no wireless connections configured in any network profile, this section of the menu is hidden.</para>
<para>For more information about changing wireless networks, see <xref linkend="chwireless-towireless"/>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Refresh Wireless Networks</guimenuitem></para>
<para>This menu item causes the list of available wireless networks and signal strengths in the menu to be re-scanned and updated. This menu item is disabled if all wireless connections are disabled in the active network profile. If there are no wireless connections configured in any network profile, this menu item is hidden.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Join Unlisted Wireless Network</guimenuitem></para>
<para>This menu item opens the <literal>Join Wireless Network</literal> dialog, when selected. Use this dialog to connect to a wireless network that is <emphasis>not</emphasis> broadcasting its network name. This menu item is disabled if all wireless connections are disabled in the active network profile. If there are no wireless connections configured in any network profile, this menu item is hidden. See <xref linkend="addjoinedit-dialog"/> for more information.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Network Modifiers</guimenuitem></para>
<para>This section contains a submenu that includes one menu entry for each network modifier that is defined in the <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialog. The menu entry for each application enables you to start or stop that application, depending on whether it is already running.</para>
<para>The icon for each entry indicates its activation type.</para>
<informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="26.42*"/>
<colspec colwidth="28.45*"/>
<colspec colwidth="44.14*"/>
<thead><row><entry><para>Icon</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Activation Type</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody><row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/condition-location.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>Conditional</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Network modifier is started and stopped automatically by user-defined rules</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/manual-location.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>Manual</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Network modifier is started and stopped manually by selection from menu or dialog</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>For more information, see <xref linkend="vpn-configuring"/>.</para>
<note><para>Conditional network modifiers are unavailable (grayed-out) because you cannot start or stop a conditional network modifier from this submenu.</para>
</note>
<para>This submenu also includes a <guimenuitem>Network Modifier Preferences</guimenuitem> menu item that opens the <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialog. See <xref linkend="vpnprefs-dialog"/>. The <guimenuitem>Network Modifier Preferences</guimenuitem> menu item is only enabled for user accounts that have been assigned the <literal>Network Autoconf Admin</literal> rights profile by a system administrator.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Network Preferences</guimenuitem></para>
<para>Opens the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog to enable you to configure your network connection. See <xref linkend="nwprefs-dialog"/>. The <guimenuitem>Network Preferences</guimenuitem> menu item is only enabled for user accounts that have been assigned the <literal>Network Autoconf Admin</literal> rights profile by a system administrator.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem></para>
<para>Opens this online help document.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Related Information</emphasis></para>
<para><xref linkend="configure-network"/>.</para>
<para><xref linkend="nwlocations-overview"/>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="viewstatus-info"><title>Obtaining Information About Your Network's Status</title>
<para>There are several ways that you can check the status of your network connection. The quickest way to obtain essential information about your network is to look at the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon that is displayed in the desktop panel's notification area at all times. The icon's appearance indicates the overall status of enabled network connections.</para>
<para>Other ways that you can obtain information about the status of your network include the following:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Hovering your mouse over the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon to display a tooltip that provides information about the status of all enabled connections.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Viewing informational messages that are displayed in the desktop panel's notification area.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Right-clicking the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon to open its menu, where the currently available locations, wireless network names, network profiles, network modifiers, and network connections are shown.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Opening the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog and switching to the <literal>Connection Status</literal> view.</para>
<para>This last method provides the most information about your currently enabled network connections.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Related Information</emphasis></para>
<para><xref linkend="nwprefs-dialog"/>.</para>
<para><xref linkend="connectstatus-view"/>.</para>
<para><xref linkend="obtainstatus-current"/>.</para>
<sect1 id="obtainstatus-current"><title>To Show Details of Enabled Network Connections</title>
<para>Open the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog, and select <guimenuitem>Connection Status</guimenuitem> from the drop-down list, if required. This method provides the most information about enabled network connections. </para>
<para>To open the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog, do one of the following:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Choose System -&gt; Administration -&gt; Network from the Main Menubar on the desktop panel.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Right click the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon to open its menu, then select the <guimenuitem>Network Preferences</guimenuitem> menu item.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/connection-status.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
<para>The list shows the status of all of the connections in the active network profile that are manually enabled and all those connections that are in the active priority group, if any. For more information, see <xref linkend="nwprofiles-configuring"/>.</para>
<para>For <emphasis role="strong">wired network connections</emphasis>, the IP address, connection speed and connection status are displayed.</para>
<para>For <emphasis role="strong">wireless network connections</emphasis>, the IP address, signal strength, connection speed connection status and security type are displayed.</para>
<para>To view the properties of a specific network connection, double-click the connection in the list. Alternately, you can open the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog, and from the <literal>Show</literal> drop-down list that is located at the top of the dialog, select a connection.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="configure-network"><title>Controlling Network Connections</title>
<para>By default, NWAM attempts to maintain a network connection at all times. If a wired network connection fails, an attempt is made to connect to one of your favorite wireless networks. If the attempt fails, other available wireless networks are tried, with your permission. For information about managing your favorite wireless networks, see <xref linkend="favorite-networks"/>.</para>
<para>You can also manually switch between wired and wireless networks, as required.</para>
<sect1 id="connectwireless-startup"><title>To Modify the Default Connection Priority</title>
<para>By default, all wired network connections take priority over all wireless network connections. That is, a wireless network connection is only attempted if a wired connection cannot be established. If more than one wireless network is available at the current location, you are prompted to select which network to join. This behavior is defined by the Automatic network profile, which is activated by default. To enforce a different behavior, you must create and activate a different network profile.</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Related Information</emphasis></para>
<para><xref linkend="addjoinedit-dialog"/></para>
<para><xref linkend="nwprofiles-configuring"/></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="chgwired-towireless"><title>To Switch From a Wired Network to a Wireless Network</title>
<para>If the Automatic network profile is active, disconnect any network cables from all enabled wired interfaces.</para>
<para>By default, if any of your favorite wireless networks are available, an attempt will be made to join them in the order in which they appear in the favorites list. Otherwise, the <literal>Wireless Chooser</literal> dialog is displayed. In this dialog you can select which network to join.</para>
<note><para>You can change the way wireless networks are joined on the <guilabel>Wireless</guilabel> tab of the <literal>Connection Properties</literal> view. See <xref linkend="connectprop-view"/>.</para>
</note>
<para>If a network profile other than the Automatic network profile is active, the method that you use to switch to a wireless network depends on the definition of that network profile.</para>
<para>Choose from one of the following methods:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Use the <guisubmenu>Connections</guisubmenu> submenu of the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon to disable the wired connection and then enable a wireless connection. Note that this method is only possible if both connections have the Manual activation type.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Edit the active network profile to enable the wired connection and disable other connections, as required.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>When the wireless connection is established, a notification message is displayed.</para>
<para>For more information, see <xref linkend="nwprofiles-configuring"/>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="chgwireless-towired"><title>To Switch From a Wireless Network to a Wired Network</title>
<para>If the Automatic network profile is active, plug a network cable into an available wired interface.</para>
<para>If a network profile other than the Automatic network profile is active, the method that you use to switch to a wired network depends on the definition of that network profile.</para>
<para>Choose from one of the following methods:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Use the <guisubmenu>Connections</guisubmenu> submenu of the <literal>Networks Status</literal> notification icon to disable the wireless connection and then enable a wired connection. Note that this method is only possible if both connections have the Manual activation type.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Edit the active network profile to enable the wired connection and disable the wireless connection.</para>
<para>When the wired connection is established, a notification message is displayed.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information, see <xref linkend="nwprofiles-configuring"/>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="chwireless-towireless"><title>To Switch From One Wireless Network to Another Wireless Network</title>
<para>If you want to join a wireless network other than the one to which you are currently connected:</para>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Right-click the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon to access its menu.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Select the wireless network of your choice.</para>
<para>If the network is secure, you might be prompted for a password.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>When the wireless connection is established, a notification message is displayed.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="chgwired-towired"><title>To Switch From One Wired Network Connection to Another Wired Network Connection</title>
<para>If you are using the Automatic network profile, it is not possible to choose which wired connection is active at any given time. The most appropriate connection is automatically chosen.</para>
<para>If a network profile other than the Automatic network profile is active, the method that you use to switch to a wired network depends on the definition of that network profile.</para>
<para>Choose from one of the following methods:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Use the <guisubmenu>Connections</guisubmenu> submenu of the <literal>Networks Status</literal> panel notification icon to enable and disable wired connections, as required. Note that this method is only possible if both connections have the Manual activation type.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Edit the active network profile to enable the required wired connection and disable the other wired connection, as required.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>When the wired connection is established, a notification message is displayed.</para>
<para>For more information, see <xref linkend="nwprofiles-configuring"/>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="addjoinedit-dialog"><title>About Joining Wireless Networks</title>
<para>By default, when any wireless network connections are enabled, NWAM attempts to connect to any available network in the favorites list, without asking, in the order in which the connections are listed. If no favorite networks are available, the <literal>Wireless Chooser</literal> dialog opens. In this dialog you can choose which wireless network to join. See <xref linkend="wireless-chooser"/>.</para>
<para>You can also modify the way in which wireless connections are attempted in the <guilabel>Wireless</guilabel> tab of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog's <literal>Connection Properties</literal> view. See <xref linkend="wirelessprops-configure"/>. If required, you can manually connect to a different wireless network by accessing the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon right-click menu. See <xref linkend="status-contxtmenu"/>.</para>
<sect1 id="join-network"><title>Joining a Wireless Network</title>
<para>By default, NWAM attempts to join the most appropriate wireless network without further intervention.</para>
<para>To manually connect to a different wireless network, you can do one of the following:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Select an available wireless network from the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon's right-click menu.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Select &#8220;Join unlisted wireless network&#8221; from the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification's icon menu.</para>
<para>An unlisted wireless network is one that has been configured so that it does not broadcast its network name, yet is still available to join.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Select an available wireless network from the <literal>Wireless Chooser</literal> dialog. The dialog is displayed automatically, when required. See <xref linkend="wireless-chooser"/>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>If you need to provide more information to complete the connection, the <literal>Join Wireless Network</literal> dialog opens.</para>
<para>In the dialog, enter the following information:</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry><term><guilabel>Network Name</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>The name of the wireless network that you want to connect to. This information is pre-filled, unless you are joining an unlisted network.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Security Type</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>A drop-down list of all the currently supported security protocols. If the network is broadcasting its network name, the security type is preselected when the dialog opens or when the network name is provided. The password field varies, depending on the security protocol that is selected.</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Three security types are supported:</emphasis></para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>None &#8211; No password is required to join the specified network.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>WEP (Wired Equivalence Privacy) &#8211; A password is required to join the specified network. A password must have either 5 or 13 ASCII characters or 10 or 26 hexadecimal digits (0-9, A-F).</para>
<para>A <guilabel>Key Index</guilabel> field is also displayed. This value is only used if a 5- or 13-character ASCII password is provided. Possible values are 1, 2, 3 or 4. If the wireless network administrator has not specified which value to use, leave the default setting, which is 1.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>WPA-PSK (Wi-Fi Protected Access Pre-Shared Key, also known as WPA Personal) &#8211; A password is required to join the specified network. The password can be between 8 and 63 ASCII characters.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Show passwords while typing</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>Check this option to see passwords displayed in plain text as you type. If unchecked, passwords will be masked as you type.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Add to favorite networks list</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>To automatically add the new network to your list of favorites, check this box.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>More Options</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>An expandable section that displays the Known BSSIDs list. This is a list of the MAC addresses of access points that are associated with this wireless network's ESSID. This information, which is optional, enables the NWAM process to distinguish different wireless networks that have the same network name. You can edit the Known BSSIDs list, adding or removing items. See <xref linkend="editing-tables"/>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>The <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button is disabled until a network name has been provided.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="wireless-chooser"><title>Working With the Wireless Chooser Dialog</title>
<para>The <literal>Wireless Chooser</literal> is a dialog that displays the wireless networks that are currently available and enables you to connect to one of them.</para>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/wireless-chooser-dlg.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
<para>The <literal>Wireless Chooser</literal> dialog opens when any of the following events occur:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>A wireless connection is attempted, but your favorite wireless networks list is empty.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>No favorite networks have been found, and the <guimenuitem>Show available networks preference</guimenuitem> has been checked on the <guimenuitem>Wireless</guimenuitem> tab of the <literal>Connection Properties</literal> view in the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>You click a panel notification message that says "Click this message to view other available networks".</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Wireless networks are listed in descending order, according to signal strength. To update the list of available networks and their signal strengths, click the <guibutton>Refresh</guibutton> button.</para>
<para>To join the selected network immediately, click <guibutton>Connect</guibutton>. If you have not joined this network before, or if you have configured your preferences so that confirmation is required, the <literal>Join Wireless Network</literal> dialog opens. Enter or confirm the password and any other security credentials that are required.</para>
<para>Clicking <guibutton>Join Unlisted</guibutton> enables you to join a network that is not broadcasting its network name. After connecting to any such network, the network is displayed in the menu and in the list of favorite networks. If the network was not added to the list of favorites when you initially connected, it will disappear from the favorites list after you disconnect or end your session.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="favorites-overview"><title>Working With Favorite Networks</title>
<para>By default, when you join a wireless network for the first time, a check box labeled, <guilabel>Add to List of Favorite Networks on Successful Connection</guilabel>, is displayed in the <literal>Join Wireless Network</literal> dialog.</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>To add the network to your list of favorites, if the connection is successful, check this box. If you do not want the network to be added to your list of favorites, uncheck the box. Note that the box is checked by default.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To add a network that is not currently available, or not currently broadcasting its network name to your favorites list, go to the <guilabel>Wireless</guilabel> tab of the <literal>Connection Properties</literal> view, then click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button. To add the network, you will need to know its network name, security type and security key. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To add unlisted or unavailable networks, remove networks, or edit networks in your favorites list, go to the <guilabel>Wireless</guilabel> tab of the <literal>Connection Properties</literal> view. See <xref linkend="favorite-networks"/>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="nwprefs-dialog"><title>About the Network Preferences Dialog</title>
<para>The <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog is where you can configure individual network connections and view the current state of each network connection. The window provides access to various views that you can switch to by using the drop-down list that is located at the top of the dialog.</para>
<para>You can open the dialog three ways:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>By selecting System > Administration > Network from the Main Menubar on the desktop panel</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>By clicking the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>By selecting the <guimenuitem>Network Preferences</guimenuitem> menu item from the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification's icon menu</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note><para>The <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog is only available to user accounts that have been assigned the <literal>Network Autoconf Admin</literal> rights profile by a system administrator.</para>
</note>
<para>At the top of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog is a drop-down list that is labeled, <guilabel>Show</guilabel>. This list enables you to switch between the <literal>Connection Status</literal> view, the <literal>Network Profile</literal> view, and the <literal>Connection Properties</literal> view for every network connection in each network profile.</para>
<sect1 id="connectstatus-view"><title> Connection Status View</title>
<para>The <literal>Connection Status</literal> view displays information about each enabled network connection in the active network profile with the Manual activation type and each connection (enabled or disabled) in the active priority group. The <guilabel>Enabled Connections</guilabel> section lists all of the enabled connections, in the same order that they are listed in the <literal>Network Profile</literal> view.</para>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/connection-status.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
<para>For each connection, the following information is shown:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Type of connection (wired or wireless)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Link name</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Current status (connected, connecting, or disconnected)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>IPv4 and IPv6 addresses, if assigned</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Information about whether addresses were obtained through DHCP (IPv4), DHCPv6 (IPv6), or Autconf (IPv6)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Signal strength (for wireless connections only)</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>A security icon that is displayed on the right side of the connection indicates whether the network is secured or unsecured. Note that this icon is only for wireless connections.</para>
<note><para>When you are in this view, you cannot change the order in which connections are attempted. To change the order in which connections are attempted, you will need to modify and activate a new network profile in the <literal>Network Profile</literal> view. For more information, see <xref linkend="nwprofiles-configuring"/>.</para>
</note>
<para><emphasis role="strong">The current status includes the following possible states:</emphasis></para>
<variablelist><varlistentry><term><guilabel>Connecting</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>A wired interface is attempting to connect, but is not yet connected.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Connected</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>A wired interface is connected.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Connecting to ESSID</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>A wireless interface is attempting to connect to the network with the given ESSID. A secure or open icon indicates whether the network is open or insecure.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Connected to ESSID</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>A wireless interface is connected to the network, with the given ESSID. The secure or open icon indicates whether the network is open or insecure.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Network unavailable</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>Wired or wireless interface is enabled, but not functional, or is unable to contact a DHCP server or gateway.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Cable unplugged</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>Wired interface is enabled, but the cable is unplugged.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Not connected</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>Wired or wireless interface is enabled, but the connection could not be established.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>To switch to the properties view of a particular connection, double-click the connection.</para>
<para>Other information that you can view or change in the <literal>Connection Status</literal> view include the following:</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry><term><guilabel>Network profile</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>Displays the name of the active network profile.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Current Location</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>Displays the active network location.</para>
<para>To open the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog, click <guibutton>Locations</guibutton>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Network Modifiers</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>Lists any network modifiers that are currently running. For example, if you were running the Cisco VPN application, the words, &#8220;CiscoVPN active&#8221;, would be displayed.</para>
<para>To open the <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialog, click <guibutton>Modifiers</guibutton>. In this dialog, you can configure, start, and stop network modifiers.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>For more information, see <xref linkend="viewstatus-info"/>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="networkprofile-view"><title>Network Profile View</title>
<para>This view enables you to configure network profiles. A network profile controls which network connections are enabled or disabled when that network profile is active. The default network profile is called Automatic. You can create additional network profiles, as required.</para>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/network-profile-view.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
<para>For more information, see <xref linkend="nwprofiles-configuring"/>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="connectprop-view"><title>Connection Properties View</title>
<para>To switch to the <literal>Connection Properties</literal> view for a specified network connection, select the connection name from the <guilabel>Show</guilabel> drop-down list or double-click the connection name while in either the <literal>Connection Status</literal> or the <literal>Network Profile</literal> view. A tabbed view appears, enabling you to view or edit the interface's properties.</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>The first tab for all connection types is the <guilabel>IP Address</guilabel> tab. Both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses can be configured on this tab.</para>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/connection-properties-ipv4.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>A <guilabel>Wireless</guilabel> tab is also displayed, if the selected connection is wireless. Here, you can configure the list of Favorite networks, and choose how the wireless interface connects to available networks.</para>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/connection-properties-wireless.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information, see <xref linkend="connectprops-config"/>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="nwprofiles-configuring"><title>Managing Network Profiles</title>
<para>A network profile specifies which network interfaces can be enabled or disabled at any given time. Using network profiles can be helpful in situations where you have more than one network interface available. For example, most modern laptop brands have both a wired and a wireless interface. Depending on your physical location, and your work environment, you might want to use only one of those interfaces and disable the other interface for security or other reasons.</para>
<para>The default network profile is called Automatic. The Automatic network profile first attempts to activate one wired connection. If the attempt fails, it then attempts to activate one wireless connection. You cannot edit the Automatic network profile. However, you can create multiple custom network profiles, as needed, each with their own behavior.</para>
<sect1 id="profile-viewinfo"><title>Viewing Available Network Profiles</title>
<para>Network profile information can be viewed in the <literal>Network profile</literal> view of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
<para>To display this view, select <literal>Network Profile</literal> in the drop-down list that is located at the top of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/network-profile-view.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
<para>The <guilabel>Network Profiles</guilabel> list displays the name of each available network profile. The currently active profile is shown with a radio button indicator. By default, there is one profile, Automatic, that you can activate but not edit or delete. However, you can create multiple additional network profiles. Network profiles that are manually created can be activated, edited, or deleted, as needed.</para>
<para>Below the Network Profiles list is a summary of the profile that is selected. To view the selected profile in full or edit the profile, click the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button.</para>
<note><para>The <emphasis>selected</emphasis> profile might be different than the <emphasis>active</emphasis> profile. </para>
</note>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="profiles-switching"><title>To Switch From One Network Profile to Another Network Profile</title>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the <literal>Network Profile</literal> view of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Select the radio button next to the network profile that you want to activate.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To switch network profiles, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> or click Cancel to close the dialog without switching profiles.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="profiles-addnew"><title>To Add or Remove a Network Profile</title>
<para>To create or edit a network profile, select <guilabel>Network Profile</guilabel> from the drop-down list that is located at the top of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>To create a new network profile, click the <guibutton>Add </guibutton> button, then type the name of the new profile.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To duplicate an existing network profile, select the profile in the list, click the <guibutton>Duplicate</guibutton> button, then type the name of the new profile.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To remove a network profile, select the profile in the list, then click the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note><para>You cannot remove the Automatic network profile.</para>
</note>
<para>For more information about editing a profile that you have added or duplicated, see <xref linkend="profiles-editing"/>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="profiles-editing"><title>Editing Network Profiles</title>
<para>When you manually add a new network profile or duplicate an existing network profile, you must edit the new profile to specify those network connections that are enabled and disabled by the new profile.</para>
<note><para>You can edit and remove a manually created network profile. However, you cannot edit or remove the Automatic network profile.</para>
</note>
<sect1 id="editprofile-opendialog"><title>Opening the Edit Network Profile Dialog</title>
<para>To edit a network profile, select the profile in the <literal>Network Profile</literal> view of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog, then click the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button.</para>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/nwprofile-auto.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
<para>The list of network profiles consists of a minimum of two top level group descriptions. For example, the Automatic profile, which is shown in the preceding figure, contains four group descriptions that are explained in more detail in the following sections.</para>
<note><para>The Automatic network profile cannot be changed or deleted. Any time the Automatic network profile is selected in the Edit Network Profile dialog, all of the profile editing buttons and drop-down lists are disabled.</para>
</note>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Always enable these connections:</emphasis></para>
<para>This group is always present in a network profile, at the top of the list. The group contains network connections that are always enabled when the network profile is active. In the Automatic network profile, there are no such connections, so "None" is shown.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Then enable any one of these connections:</emphasis></para>
<para>This is a <emphasis>priority group</emphasis> that is comprised of connections. There may be zero, one, or more priority groups in a network profile. In the Automatic network profile, this group contains all of the available wired network connections.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Else enable any one of these connections: </emphasis></para>
<para>This is another priority group. These groups are listed in priority order, so this group has a lower priority than the group that is listed above it. In the Automatic network profile, this group contains all of the available wireless network connections.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Always disable these connections:</emphasis></para>
<para>This group is always present in a network profile and appears at the bottom of the list. The group contains network connections that are always disabled when the network profile is active. In the Automatic network profile, there are no such connections, so "None" is shown.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information, see <xref linkend="prioritygrp-tasks"/>.</para>
<para>The first line of text for each network connection in the network profile displays its interface type and interface name. The second line displays its IP address and MAC address.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="enable-disable-connection"><title>To Always Enable or Always Disable Connections</title>
<para>A network connection in the "always enabled" group is always enabled when the selected network profile is active.</para>
<para>To move a network connection to the "always enabled" group, first select the connection, then do one of the following:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Enable</guibutton> button.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Up</guibutton> button until the connection moves to the &#8220;always enabled&#8221; group.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>A network connection in the "always disabled" group is always disabled when the selected network profile is active.</para>
<para> To move a network connection to the "always disabled" group, first select the connection, then do one of the following:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Disable</guibutton> button.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Down</guibutton> button until the connection moves into the "always disabled" group.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information, see <xref linkend="editprofile-opendialog"/>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="prioritygrp-tasks"><title>To Add, Edit, or Delete Priority Groups</title>
<para>You can create a network profile that treats one or more network interfaces as a group. If one or more of the interfaces in the highest priority group cannot be enabled, according to the group's priority type, then the group with the next highest priority is considered.</para>
<para>The following table describes the three different priority groups that are available.</para>
<informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="34.40*"/>
<colspec colwidth="65.60*"/>
<thead><row><entry><para>Priority Type</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody><row><entry><para><literal>Exclusive</literal></para>
</entry>
<entry><para>One connection in the group is enabled, and all the other connections are disabled. As long as at least one connection in the group is enabled (not necessarily the same one all the time), no attempt is made to enable connections in any of the lower priority groups.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><para><literal>Shared</literal></para>
</entry>
<entry><para>All of the connections in the group that can be enabled are enabled. As long as at least one connection in the group remains enabled, no attempt is made to enable connections in any of the lower priority groups.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><para><literal>All</literal></para>
</entry>
<entry><para>All of the connections in the group are enabled. If any of the connections are lost, all of the connections in the group are disabled. As long as all of the connections remain enabled, no attempt is made to enable connections in any of the lower priority groups.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>For example, the default Automatic network profile contains two exclusive priority groups. The higher priority group contains all of the <emphasis>wired</emphasis> network connections. The lower priority group contains all of the <emphasis>wireless</emphasis> network connections.</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">To Create a Priority Group:</emphasis></para>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>In the <literal>Edit Network Profile</literal> dialog, select one or more network connections to include in the priority group.</para>
<para>The <guibutton>New Group</guibutton> button is enabled when one or more network connections are selected or when the <guilabel>always enabled</guilabel> or the <guilabel>always disabled</guilabel> group description is selected.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To create a new priority group comprised of selected network connections, click the <guibutton>New Group</guibutton> button.</para>
<para>The new group, with the type Exclusive, is created. Note that this new group will have a lower priority than any of the existing priority groups.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">To Edit the Contents of a Priority Group:</emphasis></para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>To move a selected network connection in or out of a priority group, click the <guibutton>Up</guibutton> or <guibutton>Down</guibutton> button.</para>
<para>The <guibutton>Up</guibutton> button is enabled when any network connection that is not in the &#8220;always enabled&#8221; group is selected. The <guibutton>Down</guibutton> button is enabled when any network connection that is not in the <guilabel>always disabled</guilabel> group is selected.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To move a selected network connection out of its current group to a group with a higher or lower priority, which might be a priority group or the <guilabel>always enabled</guilabel> group, click the <guibutton>Up</guibutton> or <guibutton>Down</guibutton> button.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To move a selected network connection out of a priority group, which might be a priority group, or the <guilabel>always enabled</guilabel> or <guilabel>always disabled</guilabel> group, click <guibutton>Up</guibutton> or <guibutton>Down</guibutton> button. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Alternately, you can drag and drop network connections in or out of priority groups.</para>
<para>When the last network connection has been moved out of a priority group, the group no longer exists, and it is then removed from the list.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">To Change the Priority Mode of a Priority Group:</emphasis></para>
<para>To change the priority mode of a priority group, select its top-level group description or any of the connections that it contains. The <guilabel>Selected group</guilabel> drop-down list is displayed, along with the priority mode of the group that you selected.</para>
<para>To change the selected group's priority mode, choose from one of the following values in the drop-down list:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para><guilabel>Exactly one connection is enabled:</guilabel> One connection in the group is enabled and all of the other connections are disabled. This value corresponds to the <literal>Exclusive</literal> priority type.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><guilabel>One or more connections may be enabled:</guilabel> All of the connections in the group that can be enabled are enabled. This value corresponds to the <literal>Shared</literal> priority type.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><guilabel>All connections must be enabled:</guilabel> All of the connections in the group are enabled. This value corresponds to the <literal>All</literal> priority type.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">To Increase or Decrease the Priority of a Group:</emphasis></para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>To increase a group's priority, select its group description, then click the <guibutton>Up</guibutton> button.</para>
<para>The <guibutton>Up</guibutton> button is disabled if the selected group already has the highest priority in the network profile.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To decrease a group's priority, select its group description, then click the <guibutton>Down</guibutton> button.</para>
<para>The <guibutton>Down</guibutton> button is disabled if the selected group already has the lowest priority in the network profile.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">To Delete a Priority Group:</emphasis></para>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Select its group description.</para>
<para>The label of the <guibutton>New Group</guibutton> button changes to <guilabel>Remove Group</guilabel>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To remove the priority group, click <guibutton>Remove Group</guibutton>.</para>
<para>The priority group is removed from the list and no longer exists.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>Alternatively, you can delete a group by moving all of its connections into other groups.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="userprofile-addconnect"><title>To Add or Remove Connections</title>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the <literal>Edit Connections</literal> dialog by clicking the <guibutton>Connections</guibutton> button. The Connections button is enabled for all network profiles except the Automatic profile.</para>
<para>The list displays all of the connections that are currently available in the Automatic network profile.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To include a connection in the selected network profile, place a check mark by the connection.</para>
<para>To remove a connection from the network profile, remove the check mark.</para>
<note><para>One connection must be checked at all times. It is not possible to uncheck a connection if it is currently the only checked connection in the network profile.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="connectprops-config"><title>Configuring Network Connection Properties</title>
<para>Connection properties are configured in the <literal>Properties</literal> view of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog. This view enables you to choose how the IP address for a specific network interface is obtained. For wireless interfaces, this view also enables you to choose how and when wireless connections are automatically attempted. To display the network interface, select it from the <literal>Show</literal> drop-down list that is located at the top of the dialog.</para>
<para>After selecting a network interface, a tabbed view is shown, enabling you to edit the connection's properties. For all connection types, the first tab is the <literal>IP Address</literal> tab. In this tab you can configure IPv4 and IPv6 addresses. For wireless connections, a <literal>Wireless tab</literal> is also available. In this tab you can maintain a list of favorite wireless networks and choose the way a wireless interface connects to available wireless networks.</para>
<sect1 id="connectprops-setupipv4"><title>To Set Up IPv4 Addresses</title>
<para>IPv4 addresses can be assigned automatically, manually, or both, or disabled for each network interface.</para>
<para>The controls that are shown vary dynamically, based on the selection that is made from the <guilabel>IPv4 IP</guilabel> drop-down list:</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry><term><guilabel>Disabled</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>No IP address is assigned to this network connection.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>DHCP assigned</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>An IP address and subnet mask are assigned automatically for this network connection by a DHCP server on your network. If a default route is also assigned automatically, it will be displayed as read-only in the <literal>Default Route</literal> field. If a default route is not assigned automatically, you can type its IP address in the <literal>Default Route </literal> field.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Manually assigned</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>When this option is selected, you can specify a default route and one or more IP address and subnet mask pairs for the specified network connection. See <xref linkend="editing-tables"/>. </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>DHCP and Manually assigned</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>When this option is selected, one IP address and subnet mask is assigned automatically for the specified network connection by a DHCP server on your network. If a default route is also assigned automatically, it will be displayed as read-only in the <literal>Default Route</literal> field. If a default route is not assigned automatically, you can type its IP address in the <literal>Default Route</literal> field. You can also specify one or more additional IP address and subnet mask pairs. See <xref linkend="editing-tables"/>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Address Format and Validation</emphasis></para>
<para>For the manually assigned IP addresses, you can type the IP address and subnet values separately using the format, <literal>w.x.y.z</literal>. </para>
<para>Alternatively, you can provide an IP address that uses the Classless Inter-Domain Routing (CIDR) format (an IP address that is followed by a slash (<literal>/</literal> ) and a decimal number that specifies the number of consecutive bits of the subnet mask). For example, the IP address, <literal>192.168.0.0/22</literal>, represents the 1024 IPv4 addresses ranging from <literal>192.168.0.0</literal> to <literal>192.168.3.255</literal>.</para>
<para>When switching between DHCP assigned, manually assigned, and multiple IP addresses, any data that you provided previously is stored, in case you switch back to that view later. This information is also remembered between sessions.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="connectprops-setupipv6"><title>To Set Up IPv6 Addresses</title>
<para>IPv6 addresses can be assigned automatically or manually, or disabled for each network interface.</para>
<para>The controls that are shown vary dynamically, based on the selection that is made from the <literal>Current IPv6 setting</literal> drop-down list:</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry><term><guilabel>Disabled</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>No IPv6 address is assigned to this network interface.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Enabled</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>An IPv6 address is assigned automatically for this network connection by a router on your network. The router will choose whether a stateful (DHCPv6) or stateless (Autoconf) IPv6 address is assigned. If a default route is also assigned automatically, it will be displayed as read-only in the <literal>Default Route</literal> field. If a default route is not assigned automatically, you can type an IP address in the <literal>Default Route</literal> field.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Static Addresses</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>When checked, in addition to the IPv6 address (or addresses) that may be assigned automatically by DHCP or autoconfiguration, you can specify a default route and one or more IPv6 addresses. See <xref linkend="editing-tables"/>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>When switching between disabled, enabled, and static addresses, any data that you provided previously is stored, in case you switch back to that view later. This data is also remembered between sessions.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="favorite-networks"><title>To Manage a List of Favorite Wireless Networks</title>
<para>You manage your list of favorite wireless networks on the <guilabel>Wireless</guilabel> tab of the <literal>Connection Properties</literal> view. The <guilabel>Wireless</guilabel> tab becomes available when a wireless network interface is selected from the <guilabel>Show</guilabel> drop-down list that is located at the top of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
<para>For more information, see <xref linkend="favorites-overview"/>.</para>
<para>The four-column list displays your current favorite (or "bookmarked") networks, in the order in which any automatic connection will be attempted.</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>The first column displays signal strength and the network name, or the Extended Service Set Identifier (ESSID).</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>The second column displays the wireless channel.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>The third column displays the maximum transfer speed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>The fourth column displays the level of security, with secure networks indicated by an icon.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">To set the order in which connections to favorite networks are attempted, follow these steps:</emphasis></para>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog and switch to the <literal>Properties</literal> view for any wireless network connection.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To display a list of your favorite networks, click the <guilabel>Wireless</guilabel> tab.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To reorder the list, drag and drop the items to the new position or use the <guibutton>Up</guibutton> and <guibutton>Down</guibutton> buttons.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>The <guilabel>Wireless</guilabel> tab includes the following additional options:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>To add a wireless network to the list, click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button to open the <literal>Add Wireless Network</literal> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To edit a wireless network, click the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button to open the <literal>Edit Wireless Network</literal> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To delete the selected wireless network from the list, click the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The <literal>Add Wireless Network</literal> and the <literal>Edit Wireless Network</literal> dialogs enable you to add or edit the same information as the <literal>Join Wireless Network</literal> dialog. For more information, see <xref linkend="join-network"/>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="wirelessprops-configure"><title>To Configure Wireless Connection Preferences</title>
<para>Wireless connection preferences are configured on the <guilabel>Wireless</guilabel> tab of the <literal>Connection Properties</literal> view. The <guilabel>Wireless</guilabel> tab becomes available when a wireless network interface is selected from the <guilabel>Show</guilabel> drop-down list that is located at the top of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
<para>A drop-down list with the following options indicates how to proceed if no favorite networks are available when a wireless connection is attempted:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para><guilabel>Show list of available networks:</guilabel> Opens the <literal>Wireless Chooser</literal> dialog, where you can select another other wireless network to join.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><guilabel>Do not connect:</guilabel> Prevents a connection to any other wireless network until new networks are detected or a different network profile or location is selected.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Related Information</emphasis></para>
<para><xref linkend="addjoinedit-dialog"/>.</para>
<para><xref linkend="favorite-networks"/>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="nwlocations-overview"><title>Working With Locations</title>
<para>A location is a profile that comprises certain elements of a network configuration, including name service and firewall settings, which are applied together when required. For example, a laptop user might set up one location profile for a home network and another location for an office network. Because locations do not necessarily correspond to a physical location, you might also set up two different locations for use in the same workplace. One location could be used when you are connected to the company intranet. The other location could be used when you are connected to the public Internet by using a wireless access point that is located in your office.</para>
<para>Locations can be activated manually or automatically, according to environmental conditions, such as the IP address that is obtained by a network connection.</para>
<sect1 id="locationprefs-dialog"><title>About the Network Locations Dialog</title>
<para>The <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog enables you to switch locations, edit location properties, create new locations, and remove locations.</para>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/locationprefs-dialog.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
<para>To open the dialog, choose <literal>Network Locations</literal> from the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon's right-click menu. Or, from the Main Menubar on the desktop panel, choose System -&gt; Administration -&gt; Network Locations.</para>
<note><para>The <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog is only available to user accounts that have been assigned the <literal>Network Autoconf Admin</literal> rights profile by a system administrator.</para>
</note>
<para>The Locations list is similar to the list on the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification's icon menu. Each available location, with an icon that represents its activation type, is listed. </para>
<para>The following table describes the location activation types.</para>
<informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="26.42*"/>
<colspec colwidth="28.45*"/>
<colspec colwidth="44.14*"/>
<thead><row><entry><para>Icon</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Location Type</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Location Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody><row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/system-location.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>System</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Applies only to system-provided locations (Automatic and No Network). Indicates that the system determines when to activate these locations.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/manual-location.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>Manual</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Can be manually activated or deactivated by using the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog or the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/condition-location.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</entry>
<entry><para>Conditional</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Location is activated or deactivated automatically according to user-defined rules.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>The activation type of the selected location is also displayed in the <literal>Selected location</literal> drop-down list. The active location is represented by a selected radio button that is displayed in the first column of the list.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="activationmode-chg"><title>To Change a Location's Activation Mode</title>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Choose <literal>Network Locations</literal> from the desktop notification icon's right-click menu. Or, from the Main Menubar on the desktop panel, choose System > Administration > Network Locations.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To change the activation mode of a location, select the location in the list, then select the new activation mode the <guilabel>Selected location</guilabel> drop-down list.</para>
<para>Note that when a system location is selected, the drop-down list shows <guilabel>Activated by system</guilabel>, and both the drop-down list and the <guibutton>Edit Rules</guibutton> button are disabled.</para>
<para>When a Manual or a Conditional location is selected, the drop-down list options are as follows:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para><guilabel>Manual activation only</guilabel>: This location is only enabled when it is manually selected. When this option is selected, the <guibutton>Edit Rules</guibutton> button is <emphasis>disabled</emphasis>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><guilabel>Activated by rules</guilabel>: This location is automatically selected under certain network conditions. When this option is selected, the <guibutton>Edit Rules</guibutton> button is <emphasis>enabled</emphasis>. </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>(Optional) To set rules for how and when a location is activated, click the <guibutton>Edit Rules</guibutton> button. For more information, see <xref linkend="rules-dialog"/>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="locations-switching"><title>To Switch From One Location to Another Location</title>
<para>From the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon's <guisubmenu>Location</guisubmenu> submenu, choose the location that you want to activate.</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>If the <guilabel>Switch Locations Automatically</guilabel> option is selected on the <guisubmenu>Locations</guisubmenu> submenu, you cannot manually choose a location to activate. The most appropriate System or Conditional location will be activated automatically at any given time, according to changes in the network environment.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>If the <guilabel>Switch Locations Manually</guilabel> option is selected on the <guisubmenu>Location</guisubmenu> submenu, you can activate any available location, regardless of its activation type. That location remains active indefinitely.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Alternately, you can open the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog from the desktop panel applet's right-click menu. Or, from the Main Menubar on the desktop panel, choose System -&gt; Administration -&gt; Network Locations. To switch to a different location, select the radio button of that location, then click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. </para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>If the <guibutton>Switch Locations Automatically</guibutton> radio button is selected in the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog, you cannot manually choose a location to activate. The most appropriate System or Conditional location will be activated automatically at any given time, according to changes in the network environment.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>If the <guibutton>Switch Locations Manually</guibutton> radio button is selected in the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog, you can activate any available location, regardless of its activation type. That location remains active indefinitely.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="location-edit"><title>Editing Locations</title>
<para>To edit a location, open the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog by choosing <guimenuitem>Network Locations</guimenuitem> from the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon's right-click menu. Or, from the Main Menubar on the desktop panel, choose System -&gt; Preferences -&gt; Locations.</para>
<para>To edit the properties of a specified location, select the location in the list, then click <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>. </para>
<para>Alternatively, you can double-click the location in the list.</para>
<para>The <literal>Edit Location</literal> dialog opens, with the following two tabs available:</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry><term><guilabel>Name Services</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>Enables you to configure name services in the specified location.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Security</guilabel></term>
<listitem><para>Enables you to select configuration files to be used by IP Filter and IPsec features, when the specified location is active.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>To display the information to be edited, select the appropriate tab.</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Related Information</emphasis></para>
<para><xref linkend="editlocations-namesvc"/>.</para>
<para><xref linkend="editlocations-security"/>.</para>
<para><xref linkend="editlocations-smfsvc"/>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="location-confignew"><title>To Add a Location</title>
<para>New locations are added in the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog.</para>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the dialog by choosing <guimenuitem>Network Locations</guimenuitem> from the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon's right-click menu. Or, from the Main Menubar on the desktop panel, choose System -&gt; Administration -&gt; Network Locations.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To add a new location with default settings, click the <guibutton>Add </guibutton> button.</para>
<para>A new location that has the Manual activation type, is created with a temporary name. The name is selected so that you can type a new name immediately.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para> Type the name of the new location, then press <keycap>Enter</keycap> to save your changes.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To activate the location, click the radio button next to the location and then click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="location-remove"><title>To Remove a Location</title>
<para>Locations are removed in the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog.</para>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the dialog by choosing <guimenuitem>Network Locations</guimenuitem> from the Network Status notification icon's right-click menu. Or, from the Main Menubar on the desktop panel, choose System -&gt; Administration -&gt; Network Locations.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Select the location to remove, then click the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button.</para>
<para>The <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button is disabled when a system location (Automatic or No Network) is selected. These locations cannot be deleted.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To save your changes, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="location-rename"><title>To Rename a Location</title>
<para>Locations are renamed in the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog.</para>
<note><para>You can only rename a location immediately after you have added it. After you click the OK button to confirm the addition of the location and close the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog, the location name is fixed and cannot be edited.</para>
</note>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the dialog by choosing <guimenuitem>Network Locations</guimenuitem> from the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon's right-click menu. Or, from the Main Menubar on the desktop panel, choose System -&gt; Administration -&gt; Network Locations.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Select the location to rename, then click the <guibutton>Rename</guibutton> button.</para>
<para>The location name is replaced by an <emphasis>in-place</emphasis> editable text field in the list.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Type the new location name in this field, then press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.</para>
<para>To revert to the previous location name, press <keycap>Esc</keycap>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="location-duplicate"><title>To Duplicate a Location </title>
<para>Locations are duplicated in the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialog.</para>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the dialog by choosing <guimenuitem>Network Locations</guimenuitem> from the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon's right-click menu. Or, from the Main Menubar on the desktop panel, choose System -&gt; Administration -&gt; Network Locations.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Select the location, then click the <guibutton>Duplicate</guibutton> button.</para>
<para>A new location is created with a temporary name.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Type a new location name, then press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.</para>
<para>To cancel your changes, press <keycap>Esc</keycap>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To activate the location, select the radio button next to the location, then click OK.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="editlocations-namesvc"><title>To Configure Name Services For a Location</title>
<para>The name services that are used when a location is active are specified on the <guilabel>Name Services</guilabel> tab of the <literal>Edit Location</literal> dialog.</para>
<para>To specify which name services should be configured for this location, check one or more of the <guilabel>DNS</guilabel>, <guilabel>NIS</guilabel>, <guilabel>LDAP</guilabel> or <guilabel>Files</guilabel> check boxes.</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Domain Name System (DNS)</emphasis></para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Can be configured manually or through DHCP, by selecting the <guibutton>Manual</guibutton> or <guibutton>DHCP</guibutton> radio button. When configured manually, one or more name servers must be specified in the <guilabel>Servers</guilabel> text field that is provided. A domain name and search domain may optionally be specified.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Network Information Service (NIS)</emphasis></para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Can be configured manually or through DHCP, by selecting the appropriate radio button. When configured manually, a domain name must be specified in the <literal>Default Domain</literal> text field. One or more name servers may also be specified in the <literal>Servers</literal> text field.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP)</emphasis></para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Can only be configured manually. A domain name must be specified in the <literal>Default Domain</literal> text field, and one or more name servers must be specified in the <literal>Servers</literal> text field.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Files</emphasis></para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>No further configuration options are available.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Where required, multiple servers or search domains can be separated by spaces or commas.</para>
<note><para>Separate domain names cannot be specified for the NIS and LDAP protocols. Both protocols must use the same default domain name.</para>
</note>
<para>The <guibutton>Custom nsswitch file</guibutton> button enables you to choose the name service configuration file that is to be used for this location.</para>
<para>When a single name service is selected for this location, you can either use the default name service configuration file, or specify a custom configuration file. To specify a custom configuration file, click the <guibutton>Custom nsswitch file</guibutton> button to open a file chooser dialog. To revert to the default name service configuration file, click the <guibutton>Use Default</guibutton> button. The full pathname of the default configuration file that is associated with the selected name service is displayed below the <guibutton>Use Default</guibutton> button.</para>
<para>When multiple name services are selected for this location, you must always choose a custom configuration file by clicking the <guibutton>Custom nsswitch file</guibutton> button, as there is no default configuration file that can be used.</para>
<note><para>Editing the values in this dialog does not result in any changes being written to the <filename>nsswitch</filename> configuration file. Therefore, you might need to manually edit the selected file to achieve the desired behavior.</para>
</note>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="editlocations-security"><title>To Configure Security Features for a Location</title>
<para>The <guilabel>Security</guilabel> tab of the <literal>Edit Location</literal> dialog enables you to select configuration files that are used by the IPfilter and IPsec security features when a specified location is active.</para>
<para>The behavior of the check boxes and file chooser buttons are as follows:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">When you check a box</emphasis> &#8211; The corresponding file chooser button is enabled. If no file name is currently associated with the feature, a file selection dialog immediately opens. Here, you can choose a configuration file. Otherwise, the file name that was previously shown is used until you click the file chooser button.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">When you uncheck a box</emphasis> &#8211; The corresponding file chooser button is disabled. The file name that is shown iis no longer associated with that feature when the location is active. The last-used file name remains visible in the disabled control and is remembered between sessions.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="vpn-configuring"><title>Configuring Network Modifiers</title>
<para>The <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialog enables you to configure and monitor applications that temporarily change the behavior of enabled network connections. One example of a network modifier would be a virtual private network (VPN) client application.</para>
<note><para>Before you can manage network modifiers by using the <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialog, you must manually install the network modifier application or service, then complete any initial setup, such as the installation of a certificate or shared secret.</para>
</note>
<para>A network modifier can be started and stopped manually, as required. A network modifier can also be started automatically, according to user-defined rules. To be managed by using this dialog, a network modifier must either be implemented as a command-line tool, or as an SMF service.</para>
<sect1 id="vpnprefs-dialog"><title>About the Network Modifiers Dialog</title>
<para>Use this dialog to add or remove, start and stop, and edit network modifiers.</para>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="graphics/vpn-dialog.png" /></imageobject>
</mediaobject>
<para>Open the dialog using one of the following methods:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Modifiers</guibutton> button in the <literal>Connection Status</literal> view of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Right-click the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon, then select the <guimenuitem>Network Modifier Preferences</guimenuitem> menu item.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note><para>The <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialog is only available to user accounts that have been assigned the <literal>Network Autoconf Admin</literal> rights profile by a system administrator.</para>
</note>
<para>The main section of the dialog is a three-column list that displays the following information for each network modifier:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Activation state (Manual or Conditional) </para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>User-defined name, for example, &#8220;Cisco VPN&#8221;</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Current status, &#8220;Running&#8221; or &#8220;Stopped&#8221;</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The <guilabel>Start/Stop according to rules</guilabel> check box is checked if the selected network modifier has a Conditional activation type, and unchecked if the activation type is Manual. To change the activation type, toggle the check box.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="vpnapp-clicontrolled"><title>To Add a Command-Line Network Modifier</title>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the <literal>VPN Applications</literal> dialog by using one of the following methods:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Modifiers</guibutton> button in the <literal>Connection Status</literal> view of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Right-click the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon, then select the <guimenuitem>Network Modifier Preferences</guimenuitem> menu item.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Type the name of the new network modifier.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Do one of the following:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>To add a new entry that will have the Manual activation type, press <keycap>Enter</keycap> or <keycap>Tab</keycap>.</para>
<para>The two <guibutton>Manage modifiers</guibutton> radio buttons are enabled. The first of these, <guibutton>Command Line Applications</guibutton>, is selected by default. The <guilabel>Start</guilabel> and <guilabel>Stop</guilabel> command fields, and the two <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> buttons, are also enabled.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To cancel your changes, press <keycap>Esc</keycap>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Type the command that starts the network modifier into the <literal>Start Command</literal> field.</para>
<para>Alternately, you can use the <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button to open a file chooser dialog, where you can select the command to use.</para>
<para>The <guibutton>Start</guibutton> button remains disabled for the network modifier until a valid command has been typed into this field.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Type the command that stops the network modifier into the <literal>Stop Command</literal> field.</para>
<para>Alternately, you can use the <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button to open a file chooser dialog, where you can select the command to use.</para>
<para>The <guibutton>Stop</guibutton> button remains disabled for the network modifier until a valid command has been typed into this field.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To add this application, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="vpn-addservice"><title>To Add a Network Modifier Service</title>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialog by using one of the following methods:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Modifiers</guibutton> button in the <literal>Connection Status</literal> view of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Right-click the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon, then select the <guimenuitem>Network Modifier Preferences</guimenuitem> menu item.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Type the name of the new network modifier.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Do one of the following:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Press <keycap>Enter</keycap> or <keycap>Tab</keycap> to add the new entry that will have the Manual activation type, by default.</para>
<note><para>You can rename a network modifier immediately after you have added it. After you press <keycap>Enter</keycap> or <keycap>Tab</keycap> to add the new entry and close the <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialog, the network modifier name is fixed and cannot be edited.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To cancel your changes, press <keycap>Esc</keycap>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Select the <guibutton>Manage modifier using an SMF Service</guibutton> radio button.</para>
<para>When the <guibutton>Manage modifier using an SMF Service</guibutton> radio button is selected, the <literal>Service FMRI</literal> field is enabled.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Type the FMRI of the SMF service using any of the following formats:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>By specifying the absolute path:</para>
<screen><filename>svc://localhost/system/system-log:default</filename></screen>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>By specifying a path that is relative to the local system:</para>
<screen><filename>svc:/system/system-log:default</filename></screen>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>By specifying only the service identifier, with the string prefixes implied:</para>
<screen><filename>system/system-log:default</filename></screen>
<para>The <guibutton>Start</guibutton> and <guibutton>Stop</guibutton> buttons remain disabled for the network modifier until a valid FMRI has been typed in this field.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To add the service, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="vpnconfig-startstop"><title>To Start and Stop a Network Modifier</title>
<para>You can start or stop a network modifier that has a Manual activation type by selecting <guimenuitem>Start</guimenuitem> <replaceable>application-name</replaceable> or <guimenuitem>Stop</guimenuitem> <replaceable>application-name</replaceable> from the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon's <guisubmenu>Network Modifiers</guisubmenu> submenu. </para>
<para>Alternatively, you can follow these steps:</para>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialog using one of the following methods:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Modifiers</guibutton> button in the <literal>Connection Status</literal> view of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Right-click the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon, then select the <guimenuitem>Network Modifier Preferences</guimenuitem> menu item.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To start a network modifier manually, select the application in the list, then click <guibutton>Start</guibutton>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">To manually stop a network modifier:</emphasis></para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Select the application in the list, then click <guibutton>Stop</guibutton>.</para>
<para>The <guibutton>Stop</guibutton> button is enabled <emphasis>only</emphasis> for applications that are currently running.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">To automatically start and stop a network modifier:</emphasis></para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Set the application's activation type to Conditional. For more information, see <xref linkend="vpn-setrules"/>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="vpn-setrules"><title>To Set Rules for a Network Modifier</title>
<para>You can set rules that enable a network modifier to start and stop automatically.</para>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialog in one of the following ways:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Modifiers</guibutton> button in the <literal>Connection Status</literal> view of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Right-click the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon, then select the <guimenuitem>Network Modifier Preferences..</guimenuitem> menu item.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Select the network modifier for which you want to set the rule, then check the <guilabel>Start/Stop according to rules</guilabel> check box.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Edit Rules</guibutton> button to open the <literal>Edit Rules</literal> dialog. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Specify the conditions under which the selected network modifier should be started.</para>
<note><para>Whenever the conditions are no longer met, the network modifier will be stopped.</para>
</note>
<para>For more information about editing rules, see <xref linkend="rules-dialog"/>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="vpnapplication-remove"><title>To Remove a Network Modifier</title>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Open the <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialog in one of the following ways:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Modifiers</guibutton> button in the <literal>Connection Status</literal> view of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Right-click the <literal>Network Status</literal> notification icon, then select the <guimenuitem>Network Modifier Preferences</guimenuitem> menu item.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To remove a network modifier from the list, first select it, then click the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button.</para>
<para>If the selected network modifier is running, the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button is disabled. Stop the network modifier before attempting to remove it.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="gimfa"><title>Reference</title>
<para>This section includes additional instructions on the following topics:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para><xref linkend="editing-tables"/></para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="rules-dialog"/></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect1 id="editing-tables"><title>Working With Editable Tables</title>
<para>The <literal>Network Preferences</literal> and the <literal>Network Locations</literal> dialogs include tables whose contents can be edited, for example when adding multiple IP addresses in the <literal>Connection Properties</literal> view of the <literal>Network Preferences</literal> dialog.</para>
<para>When editing tables, follow these general instructions:</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Showing hidden information:</emphasis></para>
<para>If the contents of a table's cells are not fully visible, an ellipsis is displayed. To display any hidden content in a tooltip, hover your mouse over the table cell.</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Adding a new row:</emphasis></para>
<para>To add a new row, place your cursor in any empty cell, then click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button. Alternately, you can add a new row by double-clicking any cell within an empty row. Depending on the type of information that is being added, the first cell in a new row might be a text field, a combo box, or a menu.</para>
<orderedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">To complete the entry for the new cell:</emphasis></para>
<para>Type some text into the cell, or select a menu item from the drop-down list or menu. Then, press <keycap>Return</keycap> or <keycap>Tab</keycap> to move the keyboard focus to the next cell. When you have finished typing information in the last cell of a row, pressing <keycap>Return</keycap> or <keycap>Tab</keycap> moves the focus to the first cell of the next row.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">To move to another cell:</emphasis></para>
<para>To move to the next cell in a row, press the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key. To move to the previous cell in a row, press the <keycap>Shift+Tab</keycap> keys. </para>
<para>If you type any text before pressing the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key, the text remains in the cell. Note that keyboard focus wraps between rows, but not between the first and the last cell within a table.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">To cancel an entry for the entire row:</emphasis></para>
<para>To cancel or clear the information you have typed in a cell, press <keycap>Esc</keycap>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Editing a cell:</emphasis></para>
<para>To edit a cell:</para>
<orderedlist><listitem><para>Double-click the cell you want to edit.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Type the new information in the cell or select a different item from the popup menu or the drop-down list.</para>
<para>To cancel any pending changes, press <keycap>Esc</keycap>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Removing a row:</emphasis></para>
<para>There are two ways to remove a row:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Select the row by clicking any cell in the row, then click the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button.</para>
<para>Multiple rows can be selected by holding <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> or <keycap>Shift</keycap> keys while selecting the rows.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Click the Remove button while any cell in the row is being edited.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="rules-dialog"><title>Working With the Rules Dialog</title>
<para>The <literal>Rules</literal> dialog is accessed from the <literal>Network Locations</literal> and the <literal>Network Modifiers</literal> dialogs.</para>
<para>The <literal>Rules</literal> dialog enables you to specify the conditions under which certain actions should be performed, such as when a particular location should become active. </para>
<para>You create a rule by specifying one or more conditions. You then specify whether all of those conditions need to be met, or only one of the conditions needs to be met, before the action is performed.</para>
<para>If you are creating a new rule, the dialog opens with one incomplete condition shown. To complete the condition, select the condition type from the drop-down list that shows, <guilabel>Select condition</guilabel>. All of the possible condition types are listed in the following table. Note that the availability of each condition type varies, depending on the action that is performed when the conditions are met.</para>
<informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33.17*"/>
<colspec colwidth="66.83*"/>
<thead><row><entry><para>Condition Type</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Condition is true if...</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody><row><entry><para>Active connections</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>The specified network connection is (or is not) enabled and connected.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><para>Active network profile</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>The specified network profile is currently active.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><para>Any IP Address</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>The IP address of any enabled connection matches (or does not match) the specified address, or falls (or does not fall) into the specified range of addresses.</para>
<note><para>IP address ranges are specified in CIDR format (<literal>w.x.y.z/n</literal>). For example, the IP address, <literal>192.168.0.0/22</literal>, represents the 1024 IPv4 addresses ranging from <literal>192.168.0.0</literal> to <literal>192.168.3.255</literal>.</para>
</note>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><para>Any advertised domain name </para>
</entry>
<entry><para>The domain name that is advertised to any enabled connection by a DHCP server matches (or does not match) the specific domain, or contains (or does not contain) the specified string.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><para>Any system domain name</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>The domain name that is currently assigned to the system, as returned by the <command>domainname</command> command, matches (or does not match) the specified domain, or contains (or does not contain) the specified string.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><para>Current location</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>The active location matches (or does not match) the specified location.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><para>Running network modifiers</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>The specified network modifier is (or is not) currently running.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><para>Wireless network name</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Any enabled wireless interface is currently connected to a wireless network whose ESSID matches (or does not match) the specified network name, or contains (or does not contain) the specified string.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><para>Wireless network BSSID</para>
</entry>
<entry><para>Any enabled wireless interface is currently connected to a wireless network whose BSSID matches (or does not match) the specified BSSID.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>Having selected the condition type, do one of the following:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Complete the condition by choosing or typing the appropriate terms in the adjacent controls.</para>
<para>For example, to enter the condition "Wireless network name is OfficeNet", first select the condition type, <literal>Wireless network name</literal>. From the second drop-down list, select <guimenuitem>is</guimenuitem>, then type "OfficeNet" into the adjacent text field.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To add another condition, click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> (<guibutton>+</guibutton>) button that is displayed next to any existing condition. To remove an existing condition, click the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> (<guibutton>-</guibutton>) button that is displayed next to that condition.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>If the action is to be performed when any one of the conditions is met, click the <guibutton>Match Any</guibutton> button. Use the <guibutton>Match All</guibutton> button, if all of the conditions must be met before the action is performed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>To discard any changes you made to the rules since opening the dialog, click the <guibutton>Revert</guibutton> button. The dialog remains open for further editing.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter>
</book>
